=Rise of Her Lady Physician=
=صعود سيدتها الطبيبة=
=Episode 24=
=الحلقة 24=
=Rong Zelan's Eloquence Stuns the Court=
=بلاغة رونغ زيلان تذهل المحكمة=
Shouldn't you be in the Dragon Pavilion
ألا ينبغي لك أن تكون في جناح التنين؟
speaking with the Princess Consort and others?
التحدث مع الأميرة قرينة والآخرين؟
Why are you here alone enjoying the scenery?
لماذا أنت هنا وحدك تستمتع بالمناظر؟
The flower fragrance here is refreshing,
رائحة الزهور هنا منعشة،
most suitable for calming the mind.
الأكثر ملاءمة لتهدئة العقل.
Attendant Rong,
المرافق رونغ،
you've risen step by step.
لقد ارتفعت خطوة بخطوة.
Now you're favored by many.
الآن أنت مفضل لدى الكثيرين.
I'd like
أود أن
to give you a heads-up.
لأعطيك فكرة.
In the palace,
في القصر،
those who
أولئك الذين
scheme and overreach
المخطط والتجاوز
never end up well.
لا تنتهي بشكل جيد أبدًا.
What about Su Ye?
ماذا عن سو يي؟
Did she overreach?
هل تجاوزت حدودها؟
A third-class medical attendant
مساعد طبي من الدرجة الثالثة
was beaten to death only because
لقد تعرض للضرب حتى الموت فقط لأنه
she stained your clothes.
لقد لطخت ملابسك.
What about Her Highness?
ماذا عن صاحبة السمو؟
Did she overreach?
هل تجاوزت حدودها؟
She had a premature delivery for no reason.
لقد ولدت قبل أوانها دون أي سبب.
Someone has to
يجب على شخص ما أن
unravel these doubts.
كشف هذه الشكوك.
Your tongue is even sharper than your mother's.
لسانك أكثر حدة من لسان أمك.
But I wonder
ولكنني أتساءل
if you can outlive her as well.
إذا كنت تستطيع أن تعيش أطول منها أيضًا.
Your Grace, I'm flattered.
صاحب السعادة، أنا مسرور.
I will strive to live a little longer.
سأسعى للعيش لفترة أطول قليلا.
I believe
انا أؤمن
that justice will be done.
أن العدالة سوف تتحقق.
Take Lord Feng for an example.
خذ اللورد فينج كمثال.
He was fine a while ago,
لقد كان بخير منذ فترة،
yet he suddenly got executed.
وفجأة تم إعدامه.
It reminds me of the saying,
إنه يذكرني بالمثل القائل،
"God is always watching you,
"الله يراقبك دائمًا،
and retribution will
والقصاص سيكون
eventually come."
"سوف تأتي في نهاية المطاف."
You must've heard of
لا بد أنك سمعت عن
a medical attendant named Rong Zelan.
مساعد طبي يدعى رونغ زيلان.
She once controlled the spread of the plague.
لقد سيطرت ذات يوم على انتشار الطاعون.
Empress Dowager,
الإمبراطورة الأرملة
Princess Consort,
الأميرة القرينة
and Princess
والأميرة
have all benefited from her superb medical skills.
لقد استفاد الجميع من مهاراتها الطبية الرائعة.
What's more,
وما هو أكثر من ذلك،
she also helped Elder Zhong
كما ساعدت الشيخ تشونغ
develop a special medicine for treating tetanus,
تطوير دواء خاص لعلاج الكزاز،
which
أيّ
has saved countless soldiers on the battlefield.
لقد أنقذ عددًا لا يحصى من الجنود في ساحة المعركة.
Therefore,
لذلك،
I wish to appoint her as an imperial physician.
وأود أن أعينها طبيبة إمبراطورة.
Ministers,
الوزراء،
what do you think?
ماذا تعتقد؟
Your Majesty, please don't!
جلالتك، من فضلك لا تفعل ذلك!
Having a female official
وجود مسؤولة
violates our rites!
ينتهك طقوسنا!
There's no precedent
لا يوجد سابقة
for a female official throughout history.
لمسؤولة أنثى عبر التاريخ.
If the precedent is set,
إذا تم وضع السابقة،
the entire world will laugh at us!
العالم كله سوف يضحك علينا!
Please think twice!
من فضلك فكر مرتين!
Yes.
نعم.
Your Majesty, I also disagree.
جلالتك، أنا أيضا لا أتفق معك.
Our sacred principles of order are the pillars of the nation.
مبادئنا المقدسة للنظام هي ركائز الأمة.
Women must abide by the virtues.
يجب على المرأة أن تلتزم بالفضائل.
How can they be officials?
كيف يمكن أن يكونوا مسؤولين؟
Rong Zelan is skilled in medicine,
رونغ زيلان ماهر في الطب،
but she can't break the ancestral rules.
لكنها لا تستطيع كسر القواعد الأجدادية.
I agree.
أنا موافق.
Be careful with the fire.
كن حذرا مع النار.
- Be careful. - Aye.
- كن حذرا. - نعم.
Select carefully.
إختر بعناية.
- Okay. - Don't miss anything.
-حسنًا. - لا تفوت أي شيء.
Be careful.
احرص.
Sort the herbs carefully.
فرز الأعشاب بعناية.
Something's wrong!
هناك شيء خاطئ!
Have you heard?
هل سمعت؟
The ministers are arguing over Rong Zelan's appointment
الوزراء يتجادلون حول تعيين رونغ زيلان
as imperial physician!
كطبيب إمبراطوري!
Is that true?
هل هذا صحيح؟
Only men can be physicians.
لا يمكن أن يكون الأطباء إلا الرجال.
How can we allow a woman to stand as our equal?
كيف يمكننا أن نسمح للمرأة أن تقف على قدم المساواة معنا؟
- That's right. - No way.
- هذا صحيح. - لا يمكن.
Exactly.
بالضبط.
Men have always held the power in the bureau.
لقد كان الرجال دائمًا هم من يمتلكون السلطة في المكتب.
If she becomes a physician,
إذا أصبحت طبيبة،
it'd be a disaster!
سيكون كارثة!
Yes!
نعم!
Disaster!
كارثة!
We must make our stance clear!
يجب علينا أن نوضح موقفنا!
We won't share the court with women!
لن نشارك المحكمة مع النساء!
This is so unacceptable!
هذا أمر غير مقبول على الإطلاق!
We must oppose it
يجب علينا معارضته
and safeguard the ancestral rites!
وحافظوا على الطقوس الأجدادية!
Let's go to the court and ask
لنذهب إلى المحكمة ونسأل
His Majesty to retract the decree!
جلالته يتراجع عن القرار!
No female officials!
لا يوجد مسؤولات!
Let's go!
دعنا نذهب!
Let's go to the court!
دعونا نذهب إلى المحكمة!
Retract the decree!
اسحبوا القرار!
No female officials!
لا يوجد مسؤولات!
Please retract the decree!
يرجى سحب القرار!
Your Majesty, there's no precedent
جلالتك، ليس هناك سابقة
for a female official throughout history.
لمسؤولة أنثى عبر التاريخ.
Such a precedent cannot be set!
لا يمكن أن تحدث مثل هذه السابقة!
Exactly.
بالضبط.
A woman needs no talent.
المرأة لا تحتاج إلى موهبة.
How can they participate in state affairs?
كيف يمكنهم المشاركة في شؤون الدولة؟
Your Majesty.
جلالتك.
Rong Zelan has made remarkable contributions.
لقد قدمت رونغ زيلان مساهمات ملحوظة.
Please think it through!
من فضلك فكر في الأمر جيدا!
My Lords, I've heard
يا أصدقائي، لقد سمعت
you're arguing over my appointment as an imperial physician.
أنت تتجادل حول تعييني كطبيب إمبراطوري.
I wonder if I could
أتساءل عما إذا كان بإمكاني
enter the hall and speak for myself.
ادخل القاعة وتحدث عن نفسي.
Summon her.
استدعيها.
Rong Zelan, first-class attendant of the bureau,
رونغ زيلان، مساعد من الدرجة الأولى في المكتب،
bows to Your Majesty.
ينحني لجلالتك.
Your Majesty.
جلالتك.
All the imperial physicians are outside on their knees,
جميع الأطباء الإمبراطوريين بالخارج على ركبهم،
begging you to retract the decree,
أتوسل إليك أن تتراجع عن القرار،
saying, "No female officials."
قائلا "لا يوجد مسؤولات".
No female officials!
لا يوجد مسؤولات!
Retract the decree!
اسحبوا القرار!
Rong Zelan,
رونغ زيلان،
this is a rare opportunity.
هذه فرصة نادرة.
Feel free to tell
لا تتردد في إخبارنا
the ministers what you're thinking.
الوزراء ما تفكرون فيه.
Thanks, Your Majesty.
شكرا جلالتك.
I just heard you mention that
لقد سمعتك تذكر ذلك للتو
virtue for a woman lies in her lack of talent,
فضيلة المرأة تكمن في افتقارها للموهبة،
and we shouldn't participate in state affairs.
ولا ينبغي لنا أن نشارك في شؤون الدولة.
The original meaning of the saying
المعنى الأصلي للمثل
is that a woman should possess knowledge
أن تكون المرأة ذات علم
and judgment
والحكم
without showing them.
دون أن نظهرهم.
This is a rare virtue.
وهذه فضيلة نادرة.
However, since when
ومع ذلك، منذ متى
did it become a shackle that binds women?
هل أصبح قيداً يقيد المرأة؟
Huang Daopo led the people to innovate
قاد هوانغ داوبو الشعب إلى الابتكار
cotton spinning techniques,
تقنيات غزل القطن،
promoting the development of cotton weaving,
تعزيز تطوير نسج القطن،
which has benefited all.
والتي استفاد منها الجميع.
Has anyone ever said a woman like her
هل قال أحد من قبل أن امرأة مثلها
shouldn't take part in worldly affairs?
لا ينبغي أن يشارك في شؤون الدنيا؟
There's no precedent for a female official.
لا توجد سابقة لمسؤولة أنثى.
If the precedent is set,
إذا تم وضع السابقة،
it'll be a disaster!
ستكون كارثة!
Li Bing innovatively built
لي بينج مبني بشكل مبتكر
Dujiangyan Irrigation System.
نظام الري دوجيانجيان.
Cai Lun's papermaking technique had no existing model.
لم يكن لتقنية صناعة الورق التي ابتكرها كاي لون نموذج موجود.
If we never broke any rules,
إذا لم نكسر أي قواعد أبدًا،
Great Liang would still be recording events by tying knots.
لا يزال جريت ليانغ يسجل الأحداث عن طريق ربط العقد.
Moreover, a physician's duty is to heal and save lives,
علاوة على ذلك، فإن واجب الطبيب هو الشفاء وإنقاذ الأرواح،
and their skills shouldn't be judged by gender.
ولا ينبغي الحكم على مهاراتهم على أساس الجنس.
Benevolence
الإحسان
knows no gender.
لا يعرف جنسًا.
Attendant Rong
المرافق رونغ
saved Her Majesty with acupuncture
أنقذت جلالتها بالوخز بالإبر
and protected the imperial heir.
وحمى الوريث الإمبراطوري.
With such achievements,
مع هذه الإنجازات،
I can't believe you're still arguing
لا أستطيع أن أصدق أنك لا تزال تتجادل
over rites and rules.
على الطقوس والقواعد.
You're truly
أنت حقا
utterly benighted!
مظلمة تماما!
Nonsense!
هراء!
All you can do is flattering!
كل ما يمكنك فعله هو الإطراء!
Your Majesty,
جلالتك،
Rong Zelan is the daughter of the sinner Liu Fuling.
رونغ زيلان هي ابنة الخاطئ ليو فولينغ.
Sinners' children cannot become officials.
لا يمكن لأبناء الخطاة أن يصبحوا مسؤولين.
It's written in the law!
إنه مكتوب في القانون!
My Lord,
سيدي
does the Imperial City Office have any case files
هل لدى مكتب المدينة الإمبراطورية أي ملفات قضايا؟
regarding my mother's crimes?
بخصوص جرائم والدتي؟
If no case files,
إذا لم تكن هناك ملفات قضية،
how can you convict her
كيف يمكنك إدانتها؟
and accuse me of being the daughter of a sinner?
وتتهمني بأنني ابنة رجل خاطئ؟
Does the Imperial City Department have such case files?
هل يوجد لدى إدارة المدينة الإمبراطورية ملفات قضايا كهذه؟
Your Majesty,
جلالتك،
there are no files for Liu Fuling's case.
لا توجد ملفات لقضية ليو فولينغ.
Your Majesty,
جلالتك،
there are no case files,
لا توجد ملفات للقضايا،
nor have they ever handled the case.
ولم يتعاملوا مع القضية مطلقًا.
Therefore, my mother is not a sinner.
لذلك، أمي ليست خاطئة.
Back then, my mother
في ذلك الوقت، والدتي
used a topical method to treat
استخدم طريقة موضعية للعلاج
Her Majesty's asthma,
ربو جلالتها،
taking advantage of yang energy,
الاستفادة من طاقة اليانغ،
and using acrid-warm medicine to dispel the hidden phlegm.
واستخدام الأدوية الحارة لطرد البلغم الخفي.
However, due to Her Majesty's old age,
ومع ذلك، بسبب كبر سن جلالتها،
her energy was unstable,
كانت طاقتها غير مستقرة،
so it required time to take effect.
لذا فقد تطلب الأمر بعض الوقت حتى يؤتي ثماره.
You're well-paid high officials,
أنتم مسؤولون كبار ذوو رواتب عالية،
yet you know nothing
ولكنك لا تعرف شيئا
about the adaptability of medicine.
حول قابلية الطب للتكيف.
Instead, you hide behind regulations to fabricate charges.
وبدلا من ذلك، تختبئ وراء القواعد واللوائح لتلفيق التهم.
In the end,
في النهاية،
you are simply afraid
أنت خائف فقط
that the woman who once bowed to your will
أن المرأة التي انحنت ذات يوم لإرادتك
would stand as your equal
سيكون بمثابة ند لك
as a female official.
كمسؤولة.
Your constant talk of moral principles
حديثك الدائم عن المبادئ الأخلاقية
is nothing but a fig leaf to protect your power.
ليس إلا ورقة توت لحماية قوتك.
If one truly wants to benefit the people,
إذا كان أحد يريد حقًا أن ينفع الناس،
how could they use gender as an excuse
كيف يمكنهم استخدام الجنس كذريعة؟
to turn a blind eye to the suffering of women and children?
أن نغض الطرف عن معاناة النساء والأطفال؟
If one truly wants to secure the realm,
إذا أراد المرء حقًا تأمين المملكة،
they should allow women to be physicians
ينبغي أن يسمحوا للنساء بأن يصبحن طبيبات
so that all women can have access to medical care
حتى تتمكن جميع النساء من الحصول على الرعاية الطبية
and receive timely treatment.
ويتلقون العلاج في الوقت المناسب.
Your Majesty,
جلالتك،
I'm willing to dedicate my life
أنا على استعداد لتكريس حياتي
to battling against all illnesses in the world.
لمحاربة جميع الأمراض في العالم.
Your Majesty, please discard the old
جلالتك، من فضلك تخلص من القديم
to bring forth the new
لإخراج الجديد
and appoint me as
وعينني كـ
an imperial physician!
طبيب إمبراطوري!
Your Majesty, I agree.
جلالتك، أنا أوافق.
Report!
تقرير!
Your Majesty!
جلالتك!
Your Majesty, something's wrong!
جلالتك، هناك شيء خاطئ!
Two princess fell from their horses.
سقطت أميرتان من على خيولهما.
The Second Prince is in critical condition!
الأمير الثاني في حالة حرجة!
What?
ماذا؟